So they wanna get a sound level.
Could you say something?
Translate, boy. What did she say?
Sorry?
I wanna get a sound level.
Could you
say something into the microphone?
One, two, three...
Is that where you're gonna sit?
Unless you'd like me to move.
That's a good place.
As long as that's it, that's fine.
Okay, we're set.
What if recent United States efforts
to help the Latin American people
are successful?
If the ruling classes agreed
to land reforms and tax reforms,
if the standard of living could be raised,
wouldn't the message
of the Cuban revolution lose its power?
Do what you want,
but don't mess with the Americans.
It's pretty simple.
All we have to do
is organize a coup.
What did Batista do?
He led a coup and took power in one day.
The main issue is to control power.
The rest is nonsense.
It's not about taking power,
but knowing what to do with it.
- That's right.
- That coup must be based on principles.
Let's eat. Fidel is late.
Argentine!
Could you give me a hand?
It's not about making concessions
but establishing conditions.
- Sorry I'm late.
- It's about time!
Good evening. Sorry I'm late.
This is Ernesto.
- The Argentine doctor.
- Pleased to meet you.
- My pleasure.
- Let's eat!
Twenty percent of all Cubans
are permanently unemployed.
One-point-five percent of the landowners
control 46 percent of the land.
Half the population has no electricity.
Over half live in bohios.
Sorry, what's a bohio?
What's a bohio in Argentina?
A shack.
Thirty-seven percent can't read or write.
Infant mortality is through the roof.
What's more,
while the thugs of the dictatorship
gun down anyone who speaks out,
most corrupt officials
steal hundreds of millions of dollars
from the public treasury
and deposit it into
U.S. and European banks.
It's the same
in all Latin American countries.
In the last few years,
the balance of payments
between the U.S. and Cuba
has been favorable to the U.S.
by 1 billion dollars.
What does this mean?
That this poor Caribbean island
is helping to support the economy of
the most developed country in the world.
As Marti used to say,
if the U.S. takes Spain out of Cuba,
then we would have to take out the U.S.
Do you have a boat?
Money?
Not yet.
Fighters?
We've smuggled 30 into Mexico.
We'll get some more.
Do you think I'm crazy?
A little.
Well,
some craziness is good.
Fidel have extraordinary faith
that once we left for Cuba,
we would make it there,
and that once we made it to Cuba,
we would fight.
And that in fighting, we would win.
And so it was
that in November of '56,
we left Mexico in a...
A leaky boat, with 82 men onboard.
And of those 82, only 12 would survive
to witness our victory.
Murderer! Assassin!
Get out of Cuba, Che! Murderer!
Among Fidel Castro's top lieutenants,
one of the most powerful
is Major Ernesto "Che " Guevara,
the Argentine revolutionary
who became a Cuban citizen
and, as Minister of Industries,
now presides over the Cuban economy.
Major Guevara is a Marxist,
a soldier, a physician,
and the author of the classic
handbook on guerilla warfare.
He is 36 years old.
He has been called the brains
of the revolution
and the power behind Fidel Castro,
though he denies both assertions.
From this point forward,
we experienced 10 bitter days.
The only way I could walk
was to hold myself up with the trees,
or by leaning on the butt of my rifle.
As if that were not enough,
I was traveling with a soldier
who panicked every time
my asthma made me cough.
Soldiers! Soldiers
are coming! There's a lot of them!
They're going to kill us!
We have to hide!
That's Epifanio's house!
Close the door.
Where's Fidel?
My name is Ernesto Guevara.
What's yours?
Jorge Sotْs, why?
I have orders from Fidel
to command you and your men,
and lead you to where he is.
Where are you from?
Argentina.
I don't trust anyone.
I'm the only one leading these troops.
Frank Pais said to deliver these men
to Fidel, personally.
Listen! We'll stop for five minutes.
Sit down, everyone.
Hey, what's going on?
- Fidel is coming!
- Go and tell the doctor.
- Stand up, come on!
- Fidel is coming.
Stand up.
Come on, up! Grab your rifle.
Finally!
Good to see you. Are you all right?
This is Epifanio.
- Raْl.
- How are you?
Very good.
Camilo.
- How was your vacation?
- Vacation? What vacation?
Almeida.
Hello, Ramiro.
- Hi, Vilma.
- Good to see you.
Vilo.
Hello, Celia.
Thanks.
Listen.
Fidel wants to talk to you
about what happened with Sotْs.
Let him speak.
If you say something,
it could sound defensive,
and he's not going to like that.
I left you in charge
of the reinforcements.
I don't have anything
against Jorge Sotْs,
but how can you let someone with no
experience take charge of the troops?
You still have this complex about
being foreign, and it's pointless.
You trained with us,
you came in the boat with us,
you were wounded fighting with us.
You are as Cuban and revolutionary
as everyone here.
We are forming three columns.
Raْl will lead the first one.
Almeida will be in charge
of the second one.
And Jorge Sotْs
will command the third one.
I did all my studies,
finished high school,
then I worked as a mechanic
for two or three years.
I then delivered milk around the area.
Also worked as a boxer.
And in a circus, working as a magician,
among other things.
In a circus? How old are you?
Twenty.
Who gave them to you?
The one and only Celia Sلnchez!
He looks like John Wayne.
- A cowboy from the Wild West.
- The Little Cowboy.
That's it: "The Little Cowboy"!
Little Cowboy! Little Cowboy!
The army keeps moving up
and down the road, Fidel.
It would be pretty easy
to hunt a couple of patrols.
- We must be patient.
- I agree, it would be easy to do.
- We could do it fast and safely.
- No, listen a second.
If we attack one of the trucks,
then the army would say
it was a crash on the road.
But if we launch a full attack
on the Uvero barracks,
it will be impossible
for them to deny our victory.
It will have a huge psychological impact.
Do you understand?
Sotْs isn't in position,
but he can't move
because it's getting light out.
I don't know about the others.
It's hard to see because...
Fuck, I missed!
Get down!
I have a saint watching over me!
He protects me from everything!
Are you okay?
- It's my arm and leg.
- Stay calm.
Don't fall asleep.
In War and Peace,
Tolstoy remarks that military science
assumes that the bigger the army,
the stronger it is.
On the other hand,
only vaguely do they recognize
that during military combat,
the final strength of an army
is also its true physical capacity,
multiplied by one unknown "x. "
This "x " is none other
than the spirit of the troops,
measured as the greater or lesser desire
to fight and confront danger.
Men with the desire to fight,
who also understand
why they are fighting,
regardless of who they are fighting,
whether under the command
of military geniuses
or those of normal intelligence,
fighting with clubs
or with machine guns
that fire 30 rounds a minute,
these men will put themselves
in the most advantageous conditions
for fighting,
and they will triumph.
Light this up! Come on!
What are we going to do now?
Take the barracks.
Come on!
Take this, motherfuckers!
From then on,
Batista began to close
his Sierra Maestra barracks,
and Fidel was right.
It was exactly as José Marti said:
Whoever takes the Sierra Maestra
takes Cuba.
On our side, six
comrades are dead and 17 are wounded.
Of the 17, six can't walk.
How is Almeida?
He's fine. He's being treated.
Get the prisoners.
They're coming with us.
excuse me, doctor.
I have no experience
in this kind of situation.
There's a man over there
who is choking.
Okay, guys, we gotta
get out of here. Come on, they're coming.
Let's go, guys.
Leave that.
You're okay. Help him.
Che, we have to leave right now.
Hey, shithead. Leave that.
We have to go! Come on!
Israel Pardo's farm is not far.
- Ernesto can take the wounded there.
- No.
When they recover,
we can meet up with you later.
That could be very dangerous.
They're going to flood
this area with troops now.
Fidel. We don't have a choice.
Let's think about it.
Anyway, give him the best weapons.
So Fidel is off
attacking towns to the west.
Was it frustrating to you
as a revolutionary,
nursing 20 wounded men,
trying to get them inland?
A real
revolutionary goes where he is needed.
It may not be direct combat.
Sometimes it's about doing other tasks:
finding food, dressing wounds,
carrying comrades for miles
and then taking care of them
until they can take care of themselves.
This is what it means.
Was it during this period
that you discovered
what you were fighting for?
I always knew why I was fighting,
but I can tell you that it was
during the March of the Wounded
in June of 1957
that I became the fighter I am today.
And once that happens,
it leaves you only one path.
Then it seems you can never stop
being a revolutionary.
I do not have any plans to retire.
It's infected.
We'll have to leave it uncovered.
I have to walk with my ass naked?
Fuck!
Vilo smells something.
Let's pick some guavas
before going back.
Stop there, buddy.
What are you two doing here?
We're from here.
What's your name?
Israel.
Israel what?
Israel Pardo.
- What's his name?
- He's my brother, Guile.
- Ernesto Guevara.
- Did we scare you?
Guile.
Good, man, good.
We have to take him to a hospital.
Give me a swig.
Can we trust anyone
to take him out of here?
Difficult.
Soldiers tell people that the rebels
kill them and steal their food.
My mother is from here
and my father came from Haiti.
When he met my mother,
we moved to a farm that belonged
to Juanito Echevarria.
He gave us a piece
of land to grow coffee.
But we had to clear it
and plant the seeds.
And we had to give him
a third of our crop.
And one day Juanito
decided to kick us out.
When my father knew he had to leave,
he stood in front
of Juanito Echevarria and said,
"I'll leave if you want,
but you have to pay.
You have to pay me
for the four years that I worked here. "
Do you know what Juanito Echevarrيa
paid us for four years of work?
One hundred pesos.
My old man got 100 pesos
for four years.
Be careful.
Okay.
This is the bullet
I removed from your body.
You're a champ.
- I'm going to get better now.
- Yes.
COP 1 Let's go.
Keep them back, back.
Keep them back.
They have missiles aimed
at the United States.
Good morning. Would
the commander like some makeup?
- No.
- No, thank you.
You sure? All right.
Maybe a little powder.
excuse me? excuse me.
- Maybe a little powder?
- All right.
Two hundred million
Latin Americans that die of hunger.
All these people
contribute to the economic greatness
of the United States.
Revolutions are not exportable.
Revolutions are created
by the oppressive conditions
that are imposed by
the Latin American governments
against its people.
Cut.
Well done. Good job.
Listen, I'd like to ask you
a few more questions off the record.
- Should we do that?
- Yeah.
If I don't work, I don't eat.
And you are on welfare.
Go back to work in Cuba.
The people of the Third World
must be able to fight
for their own freedom,
even if this means defying
the wishes of the Soviet bloc?
Cuba doesn't align herself with blocs,
she aligns herself with justice.
The United States wants us
to pay a very high price
for the not-so-peaceful coexistence
that we live in today.
And we're willing to pay the price
that takes us to the frontiers of dignity,
not beyond.
What's the point of the U.N.
if our fate is determined by the OAS,
an organization that expelled us
and to which we no longer have ties?
excuse me, Comandante.
Will you need me tonight?
Little boy, no one is so necessary
or indispensable in this life.
Don't go thinking
that you are indispensable.
Go, do what you need to do.
I am going to give you
a little checkup...
...beginning with your ears.
Is that okay?
Ah...
Too much work and not enough to eat.
Maria, try to eat meat
whenever you can.
- All right?
- Thanks, doctor.
- Let's go, Laura.
- Goodbye.
Mommy, that guy's a liar.
He says the same thing to everyone.
- Where does it hurt?
- Nothing really hurts.
I just came to see you because
I've never seen a doctor before.
Well, you've seen one now.
I'm here for you.
excuse me.
Can I have your canteen,
so I can fill it?
Thank you, Guile.
Listen, doctor.
I want to go with you all.
First you have to learn
to read and write, man.
I can learn.
Very good, Guile.
But I still can't take you
because I don't have a gun to give you.
But I don't care, I want to help.
We need your help here.
- Good morning.
- Where do you come from?
- From Bayamo.
All of you?
If you are armed, you can stay.
If you're not,
you have to leave right now.
Esteban, come here.
Man, didn't I tell you to only
bring men with weapons?
If we're attacked, how the hell
are they going to defend themselves?
Have you been drinking?
No.
Where did you get that from?
I found it.
Hey.
Listen, what's your name?
Cuervo.
Cuervo?
How old are you?
Twenty.
They gave you a tremendous shotgun.
They must like you.
If they liked me
they'd let me keep my rifle
and not this stupid shotgun.
They would have made me
leader of a column,
and we would be fighting by now
instead of crossing these mountains.
With your permission, doctor.
We were standing guard last night
but our relief never came.
- We stayed until 6 in the morning.
- We never found out where they were.
We try to follow the rules,
but it's not easy.
Hey, Joel!
Didn't you organize
the watch last night?
Yes, sir. Why?
Omar and Carlos were on watch
for four hours and relief never showed.
Those guys are stupid shitheads.
No, you're the only shithead here.
Me? Why?
Ernesto, they should've found out
where their relief was sleeping.
- That's not my fault.
- What the fuck were you thinking?
That was your responsibility.
You organized the watch!
You had to guarantee the shift relief!
- Fuck!
- Yes, sir.
Tonight you'll stand watch
for four hours.
Stay focused!
It's ready, Che.
Esteban left to meet Cuervo
at the sentry post.
- When did he leave?
- Half an hour ago.
Those bastards are gone!
Bandera, come here.
Esteban and Cuervo took off.
We have to find both of them.
We're from Fidel's group.
We're looking for food and money.
You can put the money in this bag.
The Comandante here
wants to talk to your daughter.
We searched all over,
but nothing.
All right.
Well,
it is impossible to defeat imperialism
without identifying its head:
the United States of America.
In a capitalist system,
most people live in an invisible cage.
For example, there you accept
the myth of the self-made man,
but don't understand that
the opportunities of most people
are determined by forces
they do not even see.
This is ugly.
I want the vanguard a hundred meters
ahead of us at all times.
We should bury them.
Because yours is the kingdom,
the power and glory forever and ever.
Amen.
Che.
Locals say there's a terrible battle
in the Estrada Palma military base.
They say Raْl is wounded,
and that the army is coming toward us.
Forget about it. We're surrounded.
The only way out of here
is to cut through el Turquino.
I'm ready to take the mountain.
- Good to see you again.
- Very, very eager to meet you.
I want you to talk to Chris.
He's this guy who's writing
this fabulous book.
Are you hungry?
Would you like...?
Yes, come on,
let's get something.
I'll bring them back. Come on.
Major Guevara, I'd like to introduce you
to Senator Eugene McCarthy.
A pleasure. Pleasure, major.
He would like to thank you
for the Bay of Pigs Invasion.
There was no better way
to give the people solidarity
with its revolution
like a U.S.- backed invasion.
Some of our problems
we owe to the United States.
Others are our own fault.
Comandante, has the U.S. embargo
against Cuba
succeeded in isolating it
from the rest of Latin America?
If Cuba is ever to be completely free,
it has to be important not only
for sugar, for its sugar.
Sir, would the Comandante object
to giving me his autograph?
Good night.
That was a good party.
Vilo.
- He says he wants to talk to you.
- I'm sorry.
The problem is that one of your men
who says he is Lalo Sardiٌas
is down there with a group of rebels,
and if a patrol arrives
they're going to burn my shack
and kill my family.
And that can't happen! No way!
Pleased to meet you.
My name is Ernesto Guevara.
- What's your name?
- Emilio Cabrera.
Emilio, don't worry.
No one is going to touch anything.
Vilo, tell people to get ready,
they're about to meet Fidel Castro.
No, now listen to me.
Raْl wasn't really wounded.
We were the ones surrounding the army.
And those bastards escaped.
Boy!
Come on, motherfucker.
Give me a hug.
How are you?
Here.
- Where did you get those peasants?
- Those are my troops, man.
They're working out all right.
I don't speak out loud
because they'll get big heads.
We've missed you.
Some coffee?
Hey, Joel.
Fidel asked me
why I hadn't made you lieutenant.
I told him because you didn't know
how to read or write.
Well, I want to learn.
But I need someone to teach me.
Then get a pencil
and a pair of notebooks
and put them in your backpack.
Look, Che.
This is the new recruit
I wanted to introduce to you.
Dr. Martيnez Pلez.
- Doctor?
- Doctor.
Pleased to meet you.
I have a present here.
From now on,
I stop being the medic
to become a guerrilla.
- What, are you giving up your job?
- Yes, sir.
- Who are they?
- Chibلs and Pazos.
They're signing an agreement.
What agreement?
A political alliance.
During the early
stages of the revolution,
wasn't there a conflict between Fidel
and the urban movement?
I would say the only conflict we've had
- was with Fulgencio Batista.
- Are you saying
you had no conflict
with the urban movement?
We differed in our tactics.
They wanted to oust Batista
with a general strike,
and we wanted to overthrow him
with an armed struggle.
And as you can see,
our method proved the most effective
for removing Batista.
All right, gentlemen.
The provisional government, first, will free
all political prisoners, civilian and military.
Second, it will guarantee freedom
of information for the radio and press,
and individual and political rights
established in the 1940 Constitution.
The provisional government will also
establish terms for the Agrarian Reform
leading to the distribution
of public lands.
Have a good trip.
Excuse me, Fidel.
I can't understand how you can
meet with those clowns,
and much less, how you can
make an agreement with them.
They're fighting against
the same enemy we are.
No, you're fighting,
they're negotiating.
They have lots of followers, Ernesto.
People I can't afford to turn away.
Let's see how it goes.
But I'm sure that if we win the war,
those guys will
hand the keys over to the U.S.
Listen, when this war is won,
no one's handing any keys to anybody.
I'll guarantee you that.
Come here, I need you
to sign something for me.
It's a letter of condolence
for Frank Pais.
They killed his brother in Santiago.
They killed his brother?
Sign as "Comandante."
I'm forming a new column
on the eastern side of Mount Turquino.
You'll have three captains:
Lalo Sardiٌas,
Ramiro Valdés
and Ciro Redondo.
You have to wear out
Mosquera's troops,
harass them constantly.
Don't let up on them.
Don't even let them breathe!
You cannot give them a break.
I want you to establish a base
at el Hombrito.
Got it?
No one can leave a wounded comrade
on the battlefield.
Right?
If any of you leave weapons behind
during battle or anywhere else,
you'll have to go back for it, alone.
And if anyone falls asleep on guard duty,
he won't eat for three days.
Is that clear?
Thank you, Ciro.
I want to say something else
to make myself clear.
We respect the peasants,
so no one is allowed
to touch their harvest
or mess with them
or their families.
If anyone does,
he will be punished to the full extent
of the revolutionary code.
Luis!
Come here.
Here you go.
Take care of it like it's your girlfriend.
Thank you, Comandante.
Do you need help, Comandante?
No.
- Gustavo.
- Yes, Comandante.
Take your math notebook out
and do some work.
I'm exhausted, Comandante.
Okay.
What is the most important quality
for a revolutionary to possess?
Love.
Love?
Let me tell you something,
at the risk of sounding ridiculous.
A true revolutionary is guided
by great feelings of love:
love of humanity, of justice
and truth.
It is impossible to conceive
of an authentic revolutionary
without this one quality.
Don't move, asshole!
- Please don't shoot!
- Freeze!
I'm a doctor.
Che, they're shooting mortars!
How many men are in your troop?
One hundred forty.
Under whose command?
Merob Sosa.
- Mortars!
- Let's go.
- Tell me.
- Ramiro.
Go back and keep shooting
until Lalo Sardiٌas' squad has passed.
We'll do a second line of resistance
up there, on the hill,
200 meters away.
- See you.
- Let's go, gentlemen.
That's Gustavo!
No, Roberto! Roberto!
Are you optimistic
about the normalization of relations
between Cuba and the United States?
Friends, it would be very difficult,
it would take many, many years.
By this, I mean
with the U.S. government,
because we have nothing against
the American people.
There is not even a trace of hatred
in our country for the American people.
Comandante, there's a page missing.
- How is this possible?
- The fourteenth.
Here is the page. It's torn out.
Excuse me, Comandante.
There's a small problem.
Bomb threat at the U.N.
What did he say?
They called the station 30 minutes ago.
Hector, you go with Pedro and the
Cuban delegation in the second car,
and I will go in the first car.
I think I should go with you.
I didn't ask your opinion.
Comandante, with all due respect,
I came here to protect you.
And I'd like you to give me
that opportunity, at least.
- That way we'll die together if...
- No one is going to die.
Traitor!
Go away! Traitor! Murderer!
Not only did you desert
with your weapon
and terrorize the area,
stealing from the poor
in the name of the revolution,
but also, because of your betrayal,
peasants were tortured
and murdered by Batista's army.
Why, Esteban?
The punishment for treason is death.
And you
boasted of your authority
as a messenger for the Rebel Army,
and passing yourself off
as Comandante Almeida
you raped
Juan Carlos Estévez's daughter,
a teenager,
and this also
deserves the death penalty.
Bring him here.
Would you like a sip of rum?
Roberto, give him a swig.
Do you have a last wish?
Let me confess to Father Chلvez.
We can't bring you the priest.
He's far away, we have no time.
- Something else?
- Then give me another swig.
Give him another.
Ready.
Aim.
Make sure everyone knows
I asked for my last confession.
Fire!
Mr. President, fellow delegates.
The world has developed a great deal
in this political arena,
but American imperialism, above all,
has led people to believe
that peaceful coexistence
is the exclusive right
of the world's most powerful nations.
Cuba, my fellow delegates,
free and sovereign,
with no chains tying it to anyone,
without foreign investments
in its territory,
free from occupant military bosses
determining political status,
can stand tall at this assembly
and demonstrate the correctness
of the cry with which it was baptized.
Free territory of America!
The United States intervenes in Latin
America claiming they defend freedom.
One day this assembly
will acquire enough maturity
to demand equal rights for blacks
and Latin Americans living
in this country
as they awaken from the long, brutal sleep
to which they've been subjected.
We need to say here
something that is a known truth.
And this is a truth we have always
presented to the world.
Executions? Yes, we have executed.
We execute, and we'll continue
to execute when it is necessary.
Our fight is a fight to death.
These are the conditions
in which we live
because of the imposition
of American imperialism.
Good morning.
How are you, doctor?
- Good.
- And my brother?
Very good.
- What's your name?
- He's Enrique, my brother.
We're from Remedios.
We worked
for the 26th of July Movement.
My brother and I, with a group,
tried to burn down the stable
at the town barracks,
but one of the soldiers
identified my brother,
so we came here to find Fidel.
- What's your name?
- Rogelio Acevedo.
- How old are you, Rogelio?
- Sixteen.
- And you?
- Fourteen.
Sixteen and 14.
I can't accept you, you're too young.
- What are you here for?
- Same reasons as you.
Is that so? Very good.
Do you know how to read and write?
No.
Raise your hands, the ones
who know how to read and write.
So you know how to read and write?
Yes, Comandante.
I made it through 6th grade.
We are not here in the middle
of the mountains just to fire guns.
A country that doesn't know
how to read and write
is easy to deceive.
Since none of you have weapons,
I'm picking only eight of you.
The rest will have to go.
This is no piece of cake,
we're here to fight.
We won't eat for days.
We'll sleep on the ground in the rain.
We're risking our lives here.
Is that clear?
- Yes.
- Is that absolutely clear?
Sure?
Good. You will be a teacher.
And the rest will learn from her.
You came here to fight and to learn.
Okay?
And you?
- Come on, boys, you gotta go.
- No.
Fuck, no. You have to go.
If I have to go back to Remedios
I'd rather shoot myself.
Me too.
My God.
- Are you listening?
- Let's go, man.
Let's get moving.
Come on.
Wait, wait!
You can't do that, man.
Stand up!
You're stopping the column!
- Hold my gun.
- Let's go.
The next letter is...
No? Look.
Here. Yello...
Excuse me, Che.
He says he needs to talk to you.
What's going on?
Comandante, Camilo calls me
a bad word every time he sees me.
- What bad word?
- Something rude I don't like.
Go and get Camilo.
Like what?
I don't want to be a bother, but I'm a man
who shouldn't be disrespected.
everyone is laughing
and making fun of me.
I don't really understand
what he's saying, but I don't like it.
What's going on, Comandante?
Albertico.
What's the story?
Okay, friend, now tell me
what Camilo's been saying to you?
He calls me "vanilla piss."
Ventriloquist, man, ventriloquist.
- That's not a bad word.
- But it sounds bad. I don't like it.
A ventriloquist is someone
who talks without moving his mouth.
- Why are you calling me that?
- Yes, Camilo, why?
Because he's a good messenger
and he's always popping up
with information,
and he reminds me of a ventriloquist
puppet that moves like this.
Albertico, it's not a bad word.
It's not an insult, man.
I say it with affection.
- He's a very good messenger.
- Really?
No, it's true. He's doing things
really well. He's always there.
Yes, he is.
You wanna play ball, Che?
Today is a perfect day to abandon
the guerrilla movement.
Another chance like this
may not come along for weeks.
Let's see.
Anyone who'd like to leave
this column, step forward.
Stand up there.
Come on,
the quitters and the horses' asses!
Stay there.
I'm not leaving because I'm scared.
I have a pain and...
You are a moron. Shut up.
- My mother is sick.
- You are a moron!
You'll have to give back everything
that belongs to the column.
You're a bunch of cowards.
You have 30 minutes
to get out of here.
If we find you, you're deserters.
Israel, Roberto, take them out.
Dickhead, aren't you leaving with them?
Another faggot.
Anyone else?
So did you grow balls?
We can still stand a little bit more.
You already behaved with dignity,
but you have no chance
of adapting to this warfare.
Okay, I'll make an exception.
I'll let you take your things with you,
I'll give you a guide
and 10 pesos to each of you.
Comandante.
I think you should
forgive me in advance,
as I know you will not like
what I'm going to say.
If we joined the troops,
it wasn't to go back humiliated.
We prefer, and I speak for both,
to die on this mountain rather than
return home as failures.
We'll make the maximum effort
even if it costs our lives.
This is the last straw.
While the strong
grow weaker and leave,
these snot-nosed kids
get more courageous.
Is there any logic here?
The important ones aren't the ones
who leave, but the ones who stay
and the ones
who will join us in the future.
Listen to me.
Comandantes Raْl and Almeida
will come with me.
They will open the second
and third front with their columns.
Camilo
will replace Sardiٌas
as your new captain.
Damn.
Look how generous the revolution is.
Individualism,
the isolated action of a person
alone in a social environment,
must disappear in Cuba.
But are people built that way?
Isn't it really human nature?
It is very easy to claim
that in capitalism,
the individual has the option to satisfy
or to express true human nature.
A child has one toy and wants two.
That child gets two toys and wants four.
This is human nature, isn't it?
But when a whole society
behaves in the same way,
or when it becomes a monopoly,
oppressing the less fortunate,
is that human nature?
It is then that one has to stand up
and do something.
And aren't you acting as
an individual? Isn't Fidel an individual?
Yes, of course, we are individuals
who have accepted the challenge
and the responsibility to lead
in the name of a society as a whole.
Long live free Cuba!
Will they have much time to respond?
Each one will have 10 minutes.
- From the podium?
No, from the floor.
- And my rebuttal?
Ten minutes.
- Also from the floor?
- No, from the podium.
My government has nothing to do
with the fact that every day,
in Cuban circles, to bolster
the illusions of the Cuban people,
they announce
the formation of invading brigades
armed with revolvers
and small-caliber weapons
to confront an army that,
according to
the declarations of their leaders,
has at their disposal,
the most modern nuclear arms.
The collective and individual actions
of the governments of this hemisphere
to restrict trade with Cuba
are defensive measures,
taken in response
to Cuba's continued promotion
of subversion and violence
elsewhere in this hemisphere.
We do not support or condone
hit-and-run attacks
against ships in the Cuban trade,
or against other targets in Cuba.
The surveillance flights are authorized
by the resolution approved
by the Organization of American States
under the Rio Treaty
on 23 October 1962.
Absolutely false are the accusations
that acts of genocide are being
committed in Venezuela.
Moreover,
it is simply absurd and intolerable
that a Cuban representative
dares to make judgments
about Venezuelan sovereignty,
the unique and exclusive patrimony
of the Venezuelan people,
a truly free people,
which has a democratic government
with elections whose legitimacy
are known to the entire world.
The tragedy of the Cuban revolution
Lies in not having known how to
institutionalize this great movement
into an administration
with legal rights in the Americas.
The greatest flaw of their leaders
is that they suffer from excessive vanity
which blinds them
and prevents them
from observing past examples
which are typical of America,
like the Mexican revolution in 1910.
I, who lived many years
of my youth in Cuba,
and who perhaps
feels more than Che Guevara
that there has been
enough suffering
and pain for the Cuban people.
In my brief reply to your capricious
intervention into Panamanian issues,
I'd like to finish by saying to you:
Don't defend me, compadre.
Vilo!
Take the sick to the shelter!
To the shelter!
Take them to the shelter.
Don't run. Don't run.
Hurry up!
Come on!
One, two, three.
Polo. Take the prisoners
to your house and keep them there.
Polo. Make sure no one mistreats them,
verbally or physically.
- Understood, Roberto?
- Sure.
Come on, walk!
Che!
They killed Ciro.
They shot him in the head.
We couldn't recover his body.
May I talk to you for a second, sir?
They were very well organized.
- More than we expected?
- Much more.
They have a school, hospital,
printing press, a power plant.
They must have been here months.
What do you want me to do with this?
Torch it.
I need you to go to Minas del Frio
and create a training camp.
What for?
I want you to be personally
in charge of the new recruits.
What about my column?
Ramiro can take your place for now.
You know we're days away
from an attack.
- I don't understand.
- This is more important.
It makes sense, teach.
Who can do that better than you?
Tell me. No one, man.
Look, when this is over,
Cuba and the revolution
will need you even more.
After the loss of El Hombrito,
Fidel took away your column
and sent you to train new recruits.
- Did you feel it was a demotion?
No.
Was that what you thought at the time?
Even if I had a different opinion,
even if I felt I had been demoted,
I knew Fidel had his reasons,
and you can be sure of that.
And around this same time,
many others were trying to do this
in a more peaceful way.
Yes, that is why
Fidel backed the general strike.
But he always made it very clear
that we were the only ones capable
of defeating the enemy.
A t the outset,
a lot of the other rebel groups
didn't share Fidel's belief
that agrarian reform was a core principle
of the revolution.
What was the turning point?
How did he finally bring them around?
After the failure
of the general strike of April 9th,
there was no more doubt.
The 26th of July Movement
was the only group
that could defeat Batista.
That is what a leader does:
He convinces people to share his vision.
Are you a leader?
Do you get people to share your vision?
He wants me to tell you
that you have proved one thing
to him for sure:
He would rather face a soldier
than a journalist.
They see us rebels as agitators,
people who want to gain prestige
by complicating Batista's life.
But we don't see ourselves like that.
We see ourselves as a small army
that will become a bigger army...
Fidel has to be the commander
in chief of the entire rebellion.
But we have to propose it with tact.
Our relationship with the Communist Party
still makes people nervous.
We raised funds by naming Fidel
as leader of our revolution.
Outside of Cuba, he's the only
recognizable figure we've got.
No one is saying that
in the plains they screwed up.
But what is clear
in the Sierra Maestra
is that defeating Batista doesn't
assure the end of the dictatorship.
We also have to overthrow
Batista's army
in order to prevent another coup.
Being under the command
of the Soviet Union
isn't any better than being under
the command of the United States.
Latour, you're still thinking
like a colonized person does.
Cuba won't be under
anyone's command.
Cuba is for the Cuban people.
I'll do everything I can
with the Stalinists from the PSP,
but I don't think it will be worth it.
And we understand it, Faustino.
That's precisely why
we always want to include...
"Stalinists"?
From now on, the coordination
of the plains militias
will serve the needs
of the guerrillas in the Sierra Maestra.
Fidel Castro will become commander
in chief of all the armed forces.
Long live the revolution!
I want to congratulate you, Fidel,
because today you entered the path
of the greatest men of the Americas.
A path that
will prove to the world
it's possible to get to power
with an armed struggle
supported by the people.
It's not only me, Ernesto.
It's all of us.
This wouldn't be possible
if I were on my own.
I want you to organize a new front.
Once we start this offensive,
I want to take the war down
from the Sierra Maestra into the plains.
You'll have to unite
all the rebel factions.
We have to take control of Las Villas
Province, dividing the island in two.
Camilo's going to head in the same
direction, leading his own column.
There will be no victory in Havana
without victory in Las Villas.
Getting all the groups to work together
will be difficult, Ernesto.
So I hope you have sharpened
your political skills.
And one other thing.
I know you are very reckless,
but you can't always
put yourself on the frontline.
You are too important to us.
It's an order.
I want to respond
to the Nicaraguan delegate
even though I did not understand
his argument about accent.
I believe he referred to Cuba,
Argentina and somewhat
to Russia of the Soviet Union.
In any event,
I hope the Nicaraguan delegate found
no North American accent in my speech,
because that would be truly dangerous.
But one thing is for sure,
we don't commit assassinations
like the ones being committed
right at this moment
by the political police of Venezuela
who are called DIGEPOL
if I am not misinformed.
This police force has committed
a series of barbarous acts,
executions,
which is to say assassinations.
The Panamanian delegate,
who has been kind enough
to call me "Che"
as I am called by the Cuban people,
began speaking
about the Mexican revolution.
While Cuba spoke about the
North American massacre in Panama,
the Panamanian delegation
continued speaking in this vein,
without referring at all
to that American massacre for which
the Panamanian government broke off
relations to the United States.
On to Mr. Stevenson.
Regrettably, he is not present here.
Mr. Stevenson again claims
there is no violation of the law
that neither airplanes nor boats
leave from here and, of course,
that pirate attacks just happen.
They just come out of nowhere.
Due to the demands of imperialism,
our prime minister declared five points
to secure peace in the Caribbean.
And these are...
First:
A halt to the economic blockade
and all forms of commercial pressure
imposed by the United States
all over the world against our country.
Second: Halt all subversive activities,
such as the launch and distribution
of arms and explosives by air and water,
organization of mercenary invasions,
infiltration of spies and saboteurs,
and all actions carried out
from the territory of the United States
or accomplice countries.
Third:
Halt all pirate attacks
carried out from bases located
in the United States and Puerto Rico.
Fourth: Halt all airspace
and territorial water violations
by U.S. aircraft and warships.
Fifth: Withdrawal from
the Guantلnamo naval base
and return of Cuban territory
occupied by the U.S.
This great mass of humanity has said
"Enough!" and has stepped forward.
This march of giants will not stop
until true independence is won,
for which so many died in vain.
All of this, my fellow delegates,
is the new stance
of the American continent,
a stance captured by the cry
that is shouted
every day by our people
as an expression of our
irrefutable decision to fight,
paralyzing the strikes
of armed intruders,
an outcry that counts the support
of all the people of the world
and especially the socialist camp
headed by the Soviet Union.
This cry is " Homeland or death!"
Che!
That's Las Villas, behind the clouds.
Camilo arrived a few weeks ago
and we put ourselves under his command.
Very good.
- I see you received our supplies.
- Yes, thanks.
Of all the groups operating in the area,
the Communist Party
was the only one to send help.
I'm not surprised, Comandante.
Most of these groups
are too busy fighting each other.
Months ago, Menoyo broke from
the Directory, creating a Second Front.
Since then, each one has carved out
its own territory.
There's been open hostility
between the two factions.
Where does the 26th of July Movement
stand in all of this?
Recently,
Menoyo met with Vيctor Bordَn.
I think both groups
are on the brink
of an armed confrontation.
We're ready to cooperate
with the 26th of July Movement
in all military maneuvers.
We even agree with agrarian reform
as long as it's done reasonably
and brings in money.
Landowners should be pressured
to sell their idle land to the peasants.
But it should be sold at cost.
Will you be the one fixing the price?
How can a peasant
with no money buy land?
But what do you want?
Just give it to them?
So they can destroy it
like they did in Mexico?
The owner of the land
is the one who works it.
Comandante, you have permission
to institute agrarian reform in the region,
but the Second Front will continue
to charge the land taxes.
Menoyo, the region belongs to us all.
What we have to do here is fight.
The only thing the Directory won't do
is any kind of deal
with Menoyo's Second Front.
We'll never do business
with that bunch of bandits.
We need to attack
all the army garrisons in the area.
But you can't attack
Güinia de Miranda,
because that zone is ours.
We have more experience
and more weapons than you do.
Do you think the Americans are just
going to sit and watch this happen?
No, man, listen.
We shouldn't be doing things
so openly.
So you're one of those who think
we can make a revolution
behind the backs of the Americans?
No, man.
A real revolution cannot be hidden.
I can do more
with the 400 rifles I have
than you can with your little bazooka
and all the balls your troops may have.
Look, Peٌa, the day I have
to take arms against my comrades
will be the day I stop fighting.
If you don't take Güinia de Miranda
in five days, we'll do it ourselves.
I am Comandante Ernesto Guevara.
He is Comandante Ramiro Valdés.
And he is Captain Victor Bordَn.
I just want to say three things.
First:
From now on, I am the only one
in charge of the region of Las Villas.
Second:
We will enforce strict discipline.
And third:
The fighting is going to intensify.
Whoever is not ready to sacrifice
himself for his homeland
can leave his gun on the ground
and abandon the column
immediately.
Fire.
Give it to me, damn it!
Homeland or death!
You're ready?
Thank you.
Tell Oltuski the money
will be put to good use.
Will do.
excuse me.
The police are looking for me
in Santa Clara and want to arrest me.
I need to stay here.
I'm not going anywhere.
Well, you can stay
and work in the infirmary,
because we don't allow people
to just hang around.
I want you to know that
for the last two years
I've been working
in the clandestine movement.
I've been taking weapons, bombs
and fugitives all across the province.
I think that gives me the right
to become a guerrilla.
Okay.
We've started taxing
some of the largest landowners.
I need someone to collect the money.
You can start with that
and then we'll see.
Thanks.
Ramiro.
- The girl here will collect the taxes.
- Okay.
Finally
we were working with the other groups.
It was like a wave.
When we arrived in the towns,
people received us with open arms,
and many of them even joined us.
And you took a lot of towns
in less than a week.
Isn't it now called
"the lightning campaign "?
True, but in reality,
the battle had been building steam
for nearly 100 years.
When people hate their government,
it's not very hard to take a town.
One machine gun, 180 rifles
and 9,000 rounds of ammunition.
Victor, we need you to blow
the Cabaiguلn bridge.
The Cabaiguلn bridge? Now?
Yes. Now.
How did it go?
I couldn't collect the money.
In Placetas, the police
are looking for me too.
Rogelio!
Take the compaٌeras back to camp.
Wait a minute. With all due respect,
I know these towns like the back
of my hand. Let me be your guide.
I already have a guide.
Don't worry.
I know you're going to stay with us.
Don't be like that. Calm down, girl.
Don't worry.
Do you know Cabaiguلn?
And tell Miliلn to have his people ready.
We'll attack the garrison.
Perfect.
Che.
We have to give you a tetanus shot.
No, it might trigger
an asthma attack.
Give me some aspirin.
Comandante, this is
the Virgin of Caridad del Cobre,
the patron saint of Cuba,
to help your arrival in Havana.
I hope it helps us arrive in Placetas.
Goodbye!
- How are you? Does it hurt?
- A little, but that's unavoidable.
Here, for your arm.
Thanks.
Long live the revolution!
Shit, Argentine. You broke your paw?
- It's nothing. I fell off a roof.
- So, what happened?
- I just spoke to Fidel.
- And?
Santiago has almost surrendered.
Santa Clara is the only thing
standing between us and Havana.
Batista's throwing everything
he's got to Santa Clara.
That's why,
when you take Remedios
and I take Yaguajay,
we can then take
Santa Clara together.
Give me a light.
I know what I'm going to do
when we win this thing.
I'll put you in a cage,
tour the country and charge admission.
We'll be rich, man!
What made you join the Movement?
Well, I was in college when Fidel
attacked the Moncada Barracks.
When I read his defense plea,
" History Will Absolve Me,"
I knew he was the only one
who could take down Batista.
And that he would do it fighting,
and I liked that.
Does your family support you?
Of course.
My cousin was killed.
The brutality of the army
intensified after the general strike.
I think they got scared
when they saw
so many people against them.
You don't look like a Communist.
- And what do Communists look like?
- Well, not like you.
We come in all colors.
Do you expect to stay in Cuba
after the success of the revolution?
My wife and my daughter are in Mexico.
I have to keep them in mind.
Of course.
I'm Lieutenant Pérez Valencia.
The rebel army
is not what you have imagined.
Hand over your weapons
and no one will be injured.
Stay on the air, over.
Santa Clara hasn't sent reinforcements.
It's a lost cause for these people.
Attention, Che, attention.
Che, attention, Che.
Listen, could you resolve the problem
and follow the instructions,
the instructions, the instructions
you gave me with the man I sent?
So tell me if you understand, understand,
understand me. Over, Che.
Camilo, I hear you perfectly.
Your record is broken,
you have to change it. Over.
How long will you be
in Yaguajay? Over.
Three days, maybe a week. Over.
The more time you stay there
the harder it will be here,
Camilo. Over.
Don't dare to enter the city
without me, do you hear?
Camilo, it's fair to share
the glory sometimes. Over.
Sharing the glory is fine,
but with an Argentine,
don't do that to me.
Over and out, Che.
It's good to have you
in Santa Clara, Colonel Casillas.
The city's forces are at your disposal.
Can those forces
get me some coffee?
The best beans in the world, colonel.
Sit down.
Camilo Cienfuegos
wanted you to wait for him,
but you kept going.
Why?
Santa Clara was all they had left,
the only thing linking Havana
to the country as a whole.
And though we had not slept for days
and the army outnumbered us
nine to one,
at that point, safely waiting for Camilo
seemed to us more dangerous.
People of Santa Clara,
this is Comandante Guevara speaking.
The enemy wants us to live in fear,
but it is they who should be afraid.
The situation of the military regime
is getting worse every day,
because their soldiers
don't want to fight.
Santa Clara,
if there has ever been a time
to fight for our freedom,
that time is now.
That moment has come.
I want air strikes
all around the neighborhoods.
Torch those bastards!
He's dead.
Cover him with that sheet.
I need more help.
- Aleida.
- The situation is critical.
Talk to Camajuani
and ask for more doctors.
Yes?
Comandante, it's Rogelio
calling from the station.
Speak to me, Rogelio.
Comandante, we took the train station.
Is it safe?
Good.
Go with 15 men to the train tracks
between Toscano and San Pedro
and wait there.
All right.
The tank is screwing us.
The machine gun doesn't let us get closer.
For Guile and Ramiro.
- What's the highest position?
- The church at the end of the street.
Then you have to take the church,
you must take the church.
Of course, Comandante.
Go.
Hit it hard.
- How many houses do we have to cross?
- Five.
Little Cowboy, it's too many.
Hit it hard.
Fuck. We have to break it down now!
Get down, Little Cowboy.
You're going to get hit.
Stay here.
Aleida!
- What the fuck are you doing?
- The SIM is on the hotel rooftop.
They hit Little Cowboy.
Tamayo. What happened?
They got Little Cowboy, Comandante.
What happened to him?
We claimed a rooftop
to get a good position,
and then he got shot in the head.
They killed him.
Take him to the medical station.
Tamayo.
You are now in charge
of the suicide platoon.
Keep breaking the walls
until you reach the church.
They need to pay for this.
The rebels have surrounded the city
and our tanks can't cross the barricades.
Shit.
Get Havana on the phone.
Tell them to airlift men
from Cienfuegos.
We're going to secure this city
neighborhood by neighborhood
and street by street.
Send a battalion.
Where are you going?
I don't want to fight anymore.
I'm tired of this.
Let me go.
Anyone else want to leave?
Cease fire!
Tell your men to put down their arms.
I'm not going to negotiate
with a subordinate.
You forgot to leave your gun.
- Give me that gun.
- Take your belt off.
I said I wouldn't negotiate
with a subordinate.
That's okay. This isn't a negotiation.
Comandante,
I give you my word of honor that
if you let us return to Havana,
we won't fire another shot.
I believe your word of honor.
But I can't let those bullets kill more
Cubans. Here or anywhere else.
You have 15 minutes
to convince your men to surrender.
If not, you will be responsible
for any bloodshed.
Shit!
Send this box to Camilo in Yaguajay.
Aleida, come here.
Call them on the telephone.
We agree to a ceasefire
to get our dead and wounded.
- I advise you to surrender.
- Over my dead body.
What's wrong with you?
Where are you going?
Your colonel wants you
to fight to the death.
We don't want more Cubans to die.
Give up your weapons
and you will live.
Turn in your weapons!
Now!
Well...
The colonel and I
are going on a special mission
to check our positions.
Keep up the resistance
until I return, is that clear?
Whatever you say, colonel.
Shoot anyone who tries to leave.
Who is this?
That's Sلnchez, the police captain.
We found torture instruments
in the station.
You know,
I have an idea to take the hotel.
Tell me.
Leave it to me.
Don't shoot, don't shoot!
We surrender!
Turn in your weapons!
Come on, hurry up!
Camilo took Yaguajay and he
and his troops are heading this way.
We just heard the news
on the shortwave.
It looks like Batista
abandoned the country.
Yes, sir. Right now.
It's General Cantillo
calling from Havana.
Okay, leave.
Yes, general?
I'm negotiating
directly with the U.S. ambassador.
I'm in command of the army now,
acting on behalf of Fidel Castro.
I authorize you to negotiate a truce,
but not to surrender.
You can't surrender
under any circumstances.
As you say, general.
Captain.
I need to talk to Guevara.
I've spoken to Fidel Castro. There's
been no deal with General Cantillo.
This is a revolution, not a coup.
It's either unconditional surrender
or we'll take the garrison by force.
And you'll be responsible
for the bloodshed.
Be aware of the possibility that
the U.S. government will intervene
militarily in Cuba.
If that happens,
it would be an even bigger crime,
as you will be supporting
a foreign invasion.
In that case, your only
remaining option would be
for you to shoot yourself
for committing treason.
Mr. Guevara, I need to talk
with my superiors about that.
It's 19 minutes past 10.
At 11, I'll give the order to attack
using all our forces.
- Sir, may I return home to my family?
- No.
But we won the revolution already!
We only won the war,
the revolution begins now.
Get all your things,
we're leaving for Havana tomorrow.
Aleida. You too.
I'll need a guide.
- But I don't know Havana very well.
- Neither do I.
- This man wants to say hello to you.
- Thanks for all you've done for Cuba.
Not me, all of them. All of them.
Get ready.
We're leaving for Havana tomorrow.
He told me he was heading to Havana
to participate in a military junta
which was going to resolve
the problems of the Cuban people.
I told him murderers like him weren't
going to resolve anything anymore.
When I told him
I was bringing him to you,
he pissed in his pants.
He begged me
to take him to another chief.
What do you want me
to do with this guy?
Keep him as a prisoner of war.
He will be judged by a tribunal.
Comandante, place him
under special watch.
Sure.
- Son of a bitch.
- Bandit.
I can't see anything,
then I turn around
and I see Roberto in the jeep,
holding the grenade
with the pin still in it.
You're kidding.
So he's looking at me, smiling,
like I'm stupid.
But when he came out of the jeep,
I swear to you,
he stood up,
acting like a tough guy,
still holding the grenade in his hand,
just like this, boy.
He could barely walk because
his knees were shaking so hard,
and suddenly his eyes went up,
and then he fainted with the grenade
in his hand with the pin still in it.
Good one.
Who has a light?
Not me.
Hey, this was mine!
- Gentlemen.
- So, then?
I'm going to the capital.
Thanks for everything.
- See you in Havana.
- Of course.
Ernesto.
- Take care.
- Yes, Che.
Don't worry, my man.
Ultimately,
what we can say is that the revolution
has moments of complete madness.
The attack, for instance...
The attack, for instance,
against the Moncada Garrison,
the expedition of the Granma.
The continuous struggle
of the small group of men
that were left from that exp...
The resistance against
those last attacks by the dictatorship
in the Sierra Maestra.
The invasion of Las Villas.
The taking of the key cities in Cuba.
If you analyze each one of those things,
you come to the conclusion
that there was craziness involved.
So, then?
Are you coming with us?
Yes. Under one condition.
Which?
When we're done in Cuba,
you let me bring the revolution
to all Latin America.
You, too, are a little crazy.
It's a thing that I haven't seen
anybody doing.
The rice is the most important thing,
if you take...
Comandante,
do you need my services tonight?
Son, you're killing me.
Did I make you angry
with what I said the other night?
I'm sorry,
I don't know what I was thinking.
No, son, you are loved,
as they say in Cuba.
- Thank you, Comandante.
- Do what you need to do.
Good night.
How does it feel to be a symbol?
A symbol of what?
A symbol of the revolution.
There is one thing I can tell you.
We were very aware
that we represented the hopes
of an unredeemed America.
And all eyes, those of the oppressors
and those of the oppressed,
were fixed upon us.
In January of 1959, how old were you?
I was 30 years old.
See you in Havana!
It's Rogelio.
Tell him to stop.
- What?
- Rogelio.
Yes, tell him to stop.
What are you doing with that car?
I'm driving it to Havana.
Who gave you authorization?
I took it. It belonged
to one of the snipers, man.
Don't "man" me, Rogelio.
Even if it was Batista's,
this car isn't yours.
Go back to Santa Clara immediately
and give it back.
And then you will go to Havana
by bus, by jeep or on foot.
I'd rather walk than drive to Havana
in a stolen car. Let's go.
Unbelievable.